Eiríkur "Erik" Ernir Þorsteinsson



PROFILE

Software engineer with 11YoE. Experienced as a tech Lead, developer, and teacher. I collaborate to build future-proof applications using modern technologies and tools. I believe good software gets built by good teams, and thus emphasize team health, work-life balance, emotional safety, and diversity and inclusion in my work.

CONTACT DETAILS

- @ e.ernir@gmail.com
- +31 630962494
- ernir.net

⊠ Amsterdam, The Netherlands

PERSONAL INFORMATION

Year of birth: 1987

Citizenship: **Icelandic** (no work visa required in the Netherlands)

Languages: **English** (full professional proficiency), **Dutch** (basic), **German** (basic), **Icelandic** (native)

SKILL KEYWORDS

- Java, Python, TypeScript
- Spring, Django
- · PostgreSQL, MongoDB
- · GraphQL, RabbitMQ
- Docker, Kubernetes
- · Linux, Git

EXPERIENCE

TECH LEAD (Core Services). Picnic Technologies. **2022–current**

- Founded and trained dedicated product team working on the company's most fundamental APIs and data models, expanding the types of projects the company can tackle.
- De-risked growth by increasing stability of the company's main database cluster via a multi-team effort involving technical, architectural and organizational components.
- ♦ Led effort to introduce new warehouse orchestration system in place of a legacy monolith, allowing the company to operate new types of warehouses.

TECH LEAD (RUN Systems). *Picnic Technologies*. **2020–202**

- Led the productization of Picnic's "Runner App" used by drivers.
- ♦ Set up a GraphQL-based microservice architecture supporting both continuous feature delivery and smooth operational scale-out across markets.
- ♦ Oversaw the growth of the team from 2 engineers to 7. Enabled automated E2E testing strategies to ensure stable operations.

SOFTWARE DEV (RUN Systems). *Picnic Technologies*. **2018–2020**

Backend development of Picnic's "Runner App" used by drivers, replacing a 3rd party system. Enabled a higher service level, increased road safety, and significantly increased data insight into the last mile delivery process.

ADJUNCT FACULTY. The University of Iceland.

 \diamond Full-time university lecturer. Taught multiple courses with class sizes up to 300. Supervised TAs.

PROGRAMMING TEACHER. Technical College Reykjavík. 2013–2016

♦ Taught programming to students in the 16-20 age band. Introduced and restructured upper level courses and wrote a textbook.

LEADERSHIP SKILLS

- ♦ I emphasize team learning and growth. I am used to provide actionable, relevant performance feedback as a line manager, both formal and informal.
- ⋄ I am comfortable with being accountable for group outcomes, and growing groups to make sure goals are met. I have a proven track record of leading ambiguous, cross-team technical projects towards success.
- ♦ I am highly proactive about identifying and addressing productivity and happiness blockers I encounter in my work. I can confidently navigate conflict and steer conversations towards resolution.

SOFTWARE AND ENGINEERING SKILLS

- ⋄ I have been programming since 1998, working full time with technology for more than a decade. I consider myself a technical polyglot.
- ⋄ I am passionate about software architecture as a means to bridge everevolving business and development team needs, as well as developing longer term technical strategies.
- Recent work has focused on developing cloud microservices, backed by both relational and document databases, facilitated with message brokers.

EDUCATION

MSc Computer Science and Pedagogy. *University of Iceland*. **2014–2017** BSc Computer Science. *University of Iceland*. **2009–2013**